Yeah, am I loud and clear?
我说话清楚吗？
Yeah.
是的。
Okay, great.
好的，很好。
So good afternoon or good evening or good morning or good night,
大家下午好，傍晚好，早上好，晚上好，
wherever you are.
不管你在哪里。
Let's get started on the third lecture in 6.S081,
让我们开始学习 6.S081 的第三节课，
which is going to be about OS organization.
它是关于操作系统结构的。
And, topics for today are four things that I want to touch on.
今天我要讲的主题分为四个内容，
One is isolation,
第一个是隔离，
which you'll see is the driving design goal for OS organization.
这是由操作系统结构设计目标驱动的。
I'll talk a little bit about kernel and user mode,
我会讲一下内核模式和用户模式，
that's a way of isolating the kernel from or the operating system from user applications.
这是内核或操作系统与用户程序隔离的一种方式。
Then we'll talk about system calls,
然后我们讨论一下系统调用，
which is a way for user applications to basically transition into the kernel,
它是用户程序访问内核的一种方式。
so they can ask for services
让用户程序可以访问服务，
and we look a little bit how there's always instantiated in a [simple] form inside of xv6.
而且我们研究一下在 xv6 中是怎样实现这种[简单]形式的。
So that is the point for today.
这些就是今天的重点。
And you're still rethought of,
你还记得，
remind you where we were after the first lecture.
回忆一下第一节课的内容。
The picture in your head, that you should have in your head
你脑海中的画面，
is you know there are processes,
这里有一些进程，
like the shell, like echo, or you know whatever find,
比如 shell echo 或其他东西，比如 find ，
whatever they're some of the utilities that you implemented,
无论你实现的任何程序，
they're running on top of an operating system.
它们运行在操作系统之上。
And you know the operating system abstracts, you know some of the hardware resources,
操作系统对硬件资源进行抽象，
like disk or CPU,
比如磁盘或 CPU ，
and basically the interface between the operating systems and shells typically referred to as a system call interface,
操作系统和 shell 之间的接口通常与系统调用接口有关，
interface that we've been looking at is Unix interface.
我们考虑的接口是 Unix 接口。
And here what we see is,
这里我们要看的是，
so that was roughly you know actually with that Unix interface,
你们差不多都用过 Unix 接口，
you've been playing around in lab one, where in util lab,
在实验一 util 实验中，
you used you know the system call interface or Unix API to actually implement different sets of applications.
你使用系统调用接口或 Unix API 实现不同的应用程序。
And so lab one, util lab is mostly focused on using you know this part of the design picture here.
所以实验一 util 实验使用的是这张图片中的这一部分。
And what we're going to be doing now,
我们现在要做的是，
in this first lecture or this lecture and many subsequent lectures,
在第一节课或这节课以及后面的课程中，
we really look actually how the interface is actually implemented.
我们研究这些接口是怎样实现的。
And in fact almost all of the semester,
实际上，这学期的大部分课程，
we'll be spending time on figuring out actually how to implement interface
我们花实验弄清楚怎样实现接口，
and so this is going to be the first lecture of that kind of style.
这节课将是这类课程的第一节课。
And, fortunately, you know a lot of you asking really great questions over email
幸运的是，你们通过邮件提了一些很好的问题，
or submitted a great questions to the website,
或者在网站上提交了很好的问题，
and we won't be able to go into great amount of detail immediately
我们不会直接讲很多细节，
in this sort of first lecture that types an inside look of the operating system,
在这些深入操作系统课程中的第一节课上，
so we're going to touch on different things,
我们会涉及不同的东西，
but many things will become more clear in subsequent lectures,
但是很多东西会在后面的课程中变得更清楚，
we're going to explore in more depth.
我们会更深入地研究。
But nevertheless if there's something unclear, feel free to interrupt and ask a question.
尽管如此，如果有什么东西不清楚，可以随意打断并提问。
And maybe just to start off before actually going any further, let me ask you a question
或许在继续之前，我先问一些问题，
and sort of get the question and answering [hopefully going]
提问并回答，
and ask you like what is the most interesting thing that you've learned from the util lab.
问题是在 util 实验中你学到的最有趣的事情是什么。
And I'll start by answering that question myself,
首先，我会自己回答这个问题，
one of the things that surprise me after writing or doing the util lab is
在编写完成 util 实验后，令我惊讶的一件事是，
that I use xargs a lot more frequently than I used to do,
我比之前更多地使用 xargs ，
and another way of doing basically the same thing as xargs set of commands
与 xargs 做相同事情的其他方法，一些命令，
and after actually doing the xargs lab,
在做了 xargs 实验之后，
[] xargs has much more convenient to actually use it in that way,
以这种方式使用 xargs 更方便，
and so since then I've been a much more aggressive user of xargs
我成为一名 xargs 更积极的用户，
and I'm just wondering you know what they you know, what the experience has been for some of you.
我很想知道你们的体验是什么。
So maybe I'll call out a few names
所以，我会点名，
and maybe you can unmute your microphone and answer,
你可以关闭静音回答问题，
[] and say a little bit about your experience with util lab.
说一下你关于 util 实验的体验。
So let me pick some people, Andrew you.
我来挑几个人， Andrew You 。
Andrew, are your online listening?
Andrew ，你在线吗？
Um, the most interesting thing for me was just the pipes and how to write concurrent programs.
对我来说最有趣的东西是管道，还有如何编写并发程序。
Have you done any sort of pipe programming before, or it was the first.
你之前编写过管道编程吗，或者是第一次。
No I haven't I like seen the all concurrent stuff, but I haven't seen OS level pipes before.
不，我没有，我见过并发编程，但是没有见过操作系统管道。
How about Elizabeth Weeks?
Elizabeth Weeks ，你觉得怎么样？
Yeah, I'd agree with that, I also thought that the OS pipes are super interesting
是的，我同意这一点，我也发现操作系统管道非常有趣，
and like the primes example specifically was cool
而且质数实验也很酷，
to kind of figure out and realized that I needed to close certain pipes
理解我需要关闭当前管道，
and just like are they kind of related to each other.
它们之间有某种关联。
Yeah, probably you did find the pipes of primes are a little bit harder than you might thought,
是的，可能你会发现质数管道比你想象的要难，
this surprises me every time a little bit tricky to get right.
每次我都会感到意外，要想做对需要一些技巧。
Jessica She.
Jessica She.
Um, I also thought the primes exercise was most interesting.
我也觉得质数实验非常有趣。
Good, did it take you a lot of time or was there not too bad.
好的，它有没有花了你很长时间或者觉得还好。
Um, it took me more time after I realized my initial implementation wasn't actually concurrent,
嗯，在我意识到我的实现不是并发的之后，它花了我更多时间，
so it's interesting to think about like what the differences are there.
所以思考这之间有什么不同是很有趣的。
How about Robert Murphy?
Robert Murphy 呢？
Yeah, I think that the my experience was really just,
好的，我想我的体验是，
I found it really challenging to program in in the original way it was set up,
我发现用它设置的原始方法编程很有挑战性，
so I actually created a bunch of helper functions that wrapped around things,
所以我创建了很多很多围绕它们的帮助函数，
so that's I guess what I did.
这就是我所做的。
Okay Any might have sort of any piece of wisdom.
好的，还有人有什么想法吗？
Amanda, go ahead.
Amanda ，说吧。
I I kind of liked it and found it surprising such cool
我发现它很酷，
that stdin stdout are just file descriptors themselves zero and one.
就是标准输入和标准输出只是文件描述符 0 和 1 。
Good [], yeah xv6 doesn't hide that from you at all,
好的。 xv6 没有隐藏这个，
actually in a normal C library that will be wrapped up in a, in a, in an interface,
实际上在 C 标准库中，它会封装成接口，
but xv6 doesn't hide it for you,
但是 xv6 没有对你隐藏它，
but in the end, it boils down indeed to know just file descriptor zero one
最终，它会归结为文件描述符 0 和 1 ，
and two I guess for standard error.
还有 2 ，用来表示标准错误。
Good, Alexandra.
好的， Alexandra 。
Um, I guess, one thing I was surprised about was also from the primes problem,
我想，让我意外的一件事也是来自质数问题，
I had this bug that I spent hours on
有一个 bug 我花了很长时间，
and the thing was that I didn't realize that
就是我没有意识到，
actually they were whenever you were opening a pipe and then for- like calling fork,
当你打开一个管道，然后调用 fork ，
then basically there would be four ends to the pipe,
然后这个管道就会有四个末端，
because that pipe is kind of goes both to the child process and the process the parent process,
因为管道既连接子进程又连接父进程，
and but I was only closing two of those.
但是我只关掉了其中的两个。
So, yeah, that was.
所以，就是这样。
Yeah a common common problem.
是的，一个普遍的问题。
It made sense, but for some reason,
它有道理，但是因为某些原因，
because especially the textbook says that when you fork, all of the open file descriptors get copied,
因为，特别是书上写到当你使用 fork ，所有打开的文件描述符都会被复制，
but I don't think it that.
但是我没有想到这个。
The only way get actually really familiar with actually the program with it, experience it.
熟悉它们的方法就是用它编程，实际使用它。
Good good, well, I hope you enjoyed the lab
很好，我希望你们喜欢这个实验，
and yeah, of course I hope you enjoy the subsequent labs too.
当然，我也希望你们喜欢后面的实验。
So the lecture for today, in some sense is really you know partially
所以今天的讲座，某种意义上是
to help you to get going on the syscall lab if you haven't already started
帮助你开始 syscall 实验，如果你还没有开始的话，
and so again, you feel free to interrupt and ask questions.
还有，你可以随时打断我并提问。
Okay, so the first thing I want to do a is, talk a little bit about isolation.
好的，我想做的第一件事是，讨论一下隔离性。
And you know why it's important and why we might care.
为什么它重要，为什么我们这么关心。
You know the basic stories are a reasonable simple,
基本的描述是很简单的，
we have multiple applications here, we got the shell echo [] find
我们有很多程序在这里，比如 shell echo find ，
and it'll be [create] correct,
是由我们创建的，
if you had a bug in the shell or for example in your primes program,
如果在 shell 或质数程序中有一个 bug ，
that actually didn't affect any of the other applications,
它不会影响其他应用，
particularly it would be bad for example if it affected the shell,
特别是如果影响了 shell ，事情会变得很坏，
because probably the shell you're using to actually you know kill the program, if something goes bad.
因为如果某些东西破坏， shell 可能会杀掉程序。
So you want a strong isolation between these different applications.
所以你希望在不同的应用之间存在强隔离。
Similarly you know the OS is sort of a servant for all the applications,
类似的，操作系统为所有应用程序提供服务，
and you would like it to be the case,
你希望是这种情况，
that you know if you know you make a bug in one of your util programs,
如果你在 util 某个程序中引入一个 bug ，
that actually the operating system doesn't crash,
但是操作系统不会崩溃，
for example you pass some strange argument to the operating system,
比如你传入一些奇怪的参数给操作系统，
you know should be the case that the operating system handles that well.
也应该是这种情况，操作系统可以很好地处理。
And so again we would like to be there strong isolation between the applications and the operating system itself.
所以，我们也希望应用程序和操作系统之间有强隔离。
And one way to think about this a little bit is
一种思考方式是，
to say is ask ourselves the question, what would happen if there's actually no operating system.
问我们自己，如果没有操作系统会发生什么。
So you know consider some strawman design, design,
考虑某种 strawman 设计。
where there is no operating system,
就是没有操作系统，
or you could think about it as the operating system is [], just being a library,
或者你可以把操作系统当成 [] ，就是一个库，
you know sort of thinking about in terms of python,
从 python 的角度考虑，
maybe just import os, and import os basically loads the whole operating system inside of your application
使用 import os ，而 import os 会加载整个操作系统到应用程序，
and that's then the programming interface you use.
这就是你使用的编程接口。
And so you think about that sort of way of thinking,
你可以这样想，
so let's say we have to shell here,
这里我们有一个 shell ，
you know, maybe it includes the library for the OS
可能它包含系统库，
and maybe we have some other application echo,
我们还有其他应用程序 echo ，
and then basically you know these these applications if there's no operating system really would directly interact with the hardware,
这些应用程序，如果没有操作系统，就需要访问硬件，
for example, you know they would actually see you know there's a CPU core, there's another CPU core,
比如，它们会看到，这里有一个 CPU ，这里还有一个 CPU ，
and you know maybe there's a disk and then they interact directly with the disk blocks
这里有一个磁盘，它们直接访问磁盘，
and maybe there's memory and they were directly interact with the memory of the machine.
这里有一个内存，它们直接访问内存。
And so there's no layer between, no abstraction layer between basically the applications and the hardware
所以在应用程序和硬件之间没有抽象层，
and it turns out that it's just not such a great design for isolation.
事实证明，在隔离方面，这不是一个好的设计。
And you can see how isolation might be broken,
你可以看到隔离是怎么被打破的，
let's assume for example that you know one of the goal [] from the operating system is run multiple applications
我们假设，操作系统的一个目标是可以运行多个应用程序，
and so there has to be the case
所以肯定会有这种情况，
that once in a while, it will switch from one application to another application,
每隔一段时间，它从一个应用程序切换到另一个应用程序，
let's say the hardware has only one CPU
假设硬件只有一个 CPU ，
and so we're running the shell say about one CPU [] are periodically
所以我们在一个 CPU 上运行 shell ，周期地 [] ，
in other applications should be able to run to.
让其他应用程序也可以运行。
Well, we have no operating system to do for us,
如果没有操作系统为我们做这个，
then the shell basically has to give up, you know the CPU once in a while,
shell 就必须每隔一段时间放弃 CPU ，
and sort of be a nice person and say well I've run for a little while you get a chance to run
做一个好人，表示我已经运行一会了，现在你可以运行了，
and there's something just called cooperative scheduling.
这就是所谓的协作式调度。
But it's not so great for isolation,
但是这对于隔离来说并不好，
for example, what if some function in the shell has an infinite loop,
比如，如果 shell 中有一个无限循环，
and therefore it will never actually give up the CPU,
因此它永远不会放弃 CPU ，
and then, no other you know applications could run including maybe the application that would stop or kill the shell.
然后，没有其他应用程序可以运行，包括关闭 shell 的应用程序。
And so, we basically don't get any sort of form of enforced multiplexing,
所以，我们没有任何形式的强制复用。
that's something that we'd like to have
这是我们需要的，
where no matter what the application does, it will be forced to give up the CPU once in a while,
无论应用程序在做什么，它必须强制每隔一段时间放弃 CPU ，
that's what other applications go on.
让其他应用程序可以运行。
Similarly, if you think about this strawman design,
同样的，如果你考虑这个 strawman 设计，
you know we have there's a physical memory right
这里有一个物理内存，
and all I drew a picture here,
我画的这张图，
so the application sitting on the top of the hardware,
应用程序位于硬件之上，
but you know there's physical memory and basically the text in the code and the data for these applications actually sits in the physical memory,
这是物理内存，代码文本和程序数据在物理内存中，
it's a usual memory.
这是一个常用的内存。
And here's maybe you know the part of physical memory, that's used by the shell,
这里是 shell 使用的部分，
there's maybe a part of physical memory that's used by echo application.
这里是 echo 使用的部分。
And so you're going to, again what was see here,
所以你会再次看到，
if you'd like simply simplistically like this,
如果像这么简单，
there sure no boundary between these two guys,
这两块内存之间没有界限，
for example if you know echo store to location, for example belongs to shell like location at 1000
比如 echo 保存数据到属于 shell 的 1000 地址，
and writes value there, you know, whatever x,
并写入值 x ，
then you just overwrite the physical memory of the shell memory.
然后你就翻盖了 shell 的物理内存。
And so that you know be pretty undesirable,
这是非常错误的，
because then a bug, you know echo could actually percolate into the shell
因为产生了一个 bug ， echo 渗透到 shell 中，
and you know it's gonna be very tricky to debug that kind of stuff.
调试这类东西会非常困难，
So this basically again gives like no strong isolation.
这给我们的是非强隔离。
What we like is to have you know memory isolation,
我们想要的是内存隔离，
so that one application cannot overwrite [] memory of another application.
让一个应用程序不会覆盖另一个应用程序的内存。
Um, and, and so you know, one reason a main probably the main reason to actually have an operating system is
所以需要操作系统的一个原因是，
basically to enforce both multiplexing, in enforce strong memory isolation.
在复用的同时，有强隔离性。
If you didn't have an operating system
如果不使用操作系统
and the applications are directly interacting with the hardware
并且应用程序直接访问硬件，
would be very hard to achieve that.
是很难达到（隔离）的要求的。
So this design of basically operating system as a library is not a very common design,
所以这种将操作系统作为库的设计并不是一种很常见的设计，
you may see some real-time systems where basically applications trust each other,
你可能在一些实时系统中看到，因为它们的应用程序都是可信任的，
but in most other operating systems,
但是在大多数其他操作系统中，
you know there's an operating system that really enforce you know that kind of isolation.
有操作系统来保证这种隔离。
So if we look a little bit now, at the Unix interface from this perspective,
所以如果我们现在从这个角度看 Unix 接口，
then we see that the interface actually is carefully designed,
我们会看到这些接口是精心设计的，
so that actually is feasible to implement that enforced a isolation in terms of multiplexing, in terms of physical memory
可以方便地实现复用和物理内存方面的强隔离，
and the way that's done is that the interface basically abstracts the hardware, hardware resources,
使用的方法就是这些接口抽象了硬件资源，
in a way that then it makes it easy to actually do or not easier,
在某种程度上，更简单地，或者并不简单，
it makes it possible to provide you know the strong isolation.
它让提供强隔离成为可能。
And you know maybe you should give you some examples,
我来举几个例子，
so processes we've seen like things that are created by fork,
比如我们之前看到的由 fork 创建的进程，
you know they're not, literally a CPU, right,
它们不是真正的 CPU ，
I mean that's a correspond to what a CPU and it allows you to run computation,
我的意思是它们对应 CPU ，由 CPU 来运行计算，
but you know because you know they're the applications cannot directly interact with the CPU, but only for this process abstraction,
但是因为应用程序不能直接访问 CPU ，而是通过进程抽象，
the kernel sort of behind the scenes you know can switch between processes.
使得幕后的内核可以在进程之间切换。
So instead of having direct CPU to manipulate or given to the application,
不是直接操纵 CPU 或将 CPU 分配给应用程序，
operation system provides processes that abstract a way to the CPU itself,
操作系统提供进程作为对 CPU 的抽象，
so that actually the operating system multiplex and one CPU or multiple CPUs among multiple applications.
所以操作系统可以复用一个或多个 CPU 到多个应用程序。
Similarly, if you think about exec, exec provides a memory image, and.
同样，如果你考虑 exec ， exec 提供一个内存镜像，
Amanda, yeah, go ahead, ask your question.
Amanda ，好的，说出你的问题。
One question about processes sort of like abstracting the CPU,
一个关于进程是 CPU 的抽象的问题，
is it that one process uses part of the CPU and another process uses a more different part of that CPU
是一个进程使用 CPU 的一部分，另一个进程使用另一部分，
or a different CPU if it's like a multi-core
或者如果是多核的，使用不同的 CPU ，
or like what do you mean by processes instead of the CPU.
或者你所说的进程而不是 CPU 是什么意思。
Yeah, okay, so I really mean one CPU abstracted away into a process,
好的，我的意思是一个 CPU 抽象成一个进程，
so okay so the way to think about is the,
好的，你可以这样想，
the RISC-V core or RISC-V processor that we're using in the lab actually four cores,
我们在实验中使用的 RISC-V 处理器实际上有四个核，
and so you can run four processes concurrently or in parallel, one process on each core,
你可以同时运行四个进程，每个核一个进程，
and what the operating system does is,
操作系统说做的就是，
let's say you have eight applications or seven applications,
比如你有八个或七个应用程序，
it will take some core and multiplex it, time multiplex it between different processes,
它会使用一些核，并通过时间复用，在不同的进程上，
so for example it will run you one application process for 100 milliseconds,
比如它会运行一个应用程序进程 100 微秒，
then stop, unload that process out of the CPU or out of the core,
然后停止，从 CPU 或内核中卸载进程，
loading the next application, or the next process that runs out for 100 milliseconds
加载下一个应用程序进程，并运行 100 毫秒，
and it just enforces that no application can run or no process can run longer than a hundred milliseconds.
它保证没有应用程序或进程运行超过 100 毫秒。
We'll see exactly how this was done in a couple lectures,
我们将会在后面的课程中看到这是如何实现的，
but that's sort of the basic idea.
但这就是它的基本思想。
Okay, but multiple processes cannot use the same CPU at the same time.
好的，但是多个进程不能同时使用相同的 CPU 。
No it's time multiplexing.
是的，它是时间复用的。
You run one for a while then you run the next one for a while.
你运行一个一段时间，然后再运行下一个一段时间。
Alright, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so a one way to think about exec is that it's a abstracts memory.
好的，所以考虑 exec 的一种方式是，它是对内存的抽象。
So, for example if you think about,
比如你想，
the exec system call you know takes a file name,
exec 系统调用使用一个文件名，
you know and in that file is basically the memory image of a program,
在那个文件中是一个程序镜像，
stored text, so it's a global data in, that forms the memory of the application,
保存了 text , global data ，这些组成了应用程序的内存，
now the application can grow its memory,
应用程序可以增加内存，
for example by calling sbrk and extend there by extending its data segment,
比如通过调用 sbrk ，扩展其数据段，
but it doesn't really have a direct aspects to physical memory,
但是实际上对物理内存没有直接影响，
you know you can't just ask I want you know addresses into physical memory, 1k to 2k,
你不能要求访问物理内存 1k 或 2k ，
there's no way of getting at that
没有方法可以做到这个，
and again the reason there's no way that you can get at that is
再次强调，没有方法做到这个的原因是，
because the operating system needs to want to provide memory isolation
因为操作系统提供内存隔离，
and therefore what's being controlled intermediate intermediate between the applications and the physical hardware.
因此控制了应用程序和物理硬件之间的交互。
And exec is a sort of a system call that you know captures or shows that there's no direct access to memory.
exec 系统调用，展示了不能直接访问内存。
Another example, this is like files,
另一个例子是文件，
the files basically abstract away disk blocks,
文件是对磁盘块的抽象，
instead of reading or writing the disk blocks of the disk, that's attached to your computer,
而不是直接读写计算机磁盘的磁盘块，
that actually just not allowed in Unix,
实际上，这在 Unix 上是不允许的，
you know the only way to interact with the storage system is through files,
你访问存储系统的唯一方法就是通过文件，
and you can read or write files, provide a convenient abstraction, you can name files, etc etc,
你可以读写文件，它提供了很方便的抽象，命名文件等等，
but then the operating system in itself can actually decide how to map those files to disk blocks
然后操作系统自己决定如何对文件到磁盘块做映射，
and make sure for example of disk block only shows up in one file
保证磁盘块只会出现在一个文件中，
and that you know user a cannot actually you know manipulate to read or write you know the files of user b,
保证用户 a 不能读写用户 b 的文件。
and again you know this, you know that sort of interface that the file abstraction allows that sort of strong isolation
你知道文件抽象接口提供了强隔离，
between different users and different processes of the same user.
在不同用户之间，或者相同用户的不同进程之间。
As you can see,
如你所见，
that in some ways you know the system call interface Unix interface giving programming with you know in the util lab,
在某些方面， Unix 接口，比如在 util 实验中使用的，
seems to be sort of carefully designed to abstract the resources in way,
是经过精心设计的，以一种方式对资源进行抽象，
so that you know the operating system, the implementation of the interface can actually multiply the resource of multiple applications and provide strong strong isolation.
操作系统或接口可以对多个进程复用资源，并提供强隔离。
Any questions about that?
这个有什么问题吗？
We have a question in the chat,
我们在聊天中有一个问题，
that says do more complex kernels try to reschedule processes on the same core to reduce cache misses.
问题是是否更复杂的内核会试着重新调度同一个核的进程，以减少缓存缺失。
Oh, yeah, there there's something called cache affinity,
是的，有一个叫做缓存亲和性的东西，
you know this conversion in a modern operating systems are very sophisticated
现代操作系统中的这种转换非常复杂，
and indeed you know trying to avoid cache misses and things like that and to optimise the performance.
试着避免缓存缺失或类似的事情来优化性能。
And you will see some of them much later in the semester
你会在本学期晚些时候看到其中一些，
where we are going to be talking about high performence networking,
那里我们会讨论高性能网络，
will show up there.
它们也会出现在那里。
Another question from chat,
聊天中的另一个问题，
where in xv6 can we see how the OS multiplex processes.
在 xv6 中，哪里可以看到操作系统复用进程。
There's a couple files that are relevant, but proc.c is probably the most relevant one,
有一些相关的文件，但是 proc.c 可能是最相关的那个，
this will be a topic of lecture in like two or three weeks,
这将是两三周后课程的主题，
and we're going to go in great amount of detail and show exactly how the multiplex happens.
我们将深入细节，展示复用是如何发生的。
So one way to think about this lecture a little bit of an introduction to a lot of different pieces
所以你可以把这节课当成是很多不同部分的简介，
and you know because we've got to start somewhere.
因为我们必须从某个地方开始。
Okay, so we go back into this picture here, that I showed a little while ago,
好的，让我们回到之前的图片，
currently we have this shell running, the echo running,
当前我们有 shell 在运行，有 echo 在运行，
um, not that picture, this picture here on this side,
不是那张图，是这张，在这边，
we've got the operating system, we have the applications running
我们有操作系统，有应用程序运行，
and one thing we should be worried about this were that
我们应该考虑的一件事是，
the operating system should be it should be defensive.
操作系统应该是防御性的。
This is sort of an important, a mindset you know that you have to get used to once you doing kernel development,
当你做内核开发时，这是一种重要的思维模式，
the operating system has to ensure that everything you know everything works out
操作系统必须确保任何东西都能正常运行，
and so it has to set up things up, so that you know an app cannot crash the operating system.
所以它必须设置一些东西，防止应用程序破坏操作系统。
It would be too bad
以下情况是很糟糕的，
if an application, that either by accident or maliciously passers are tricky heartened bad argument to the operating system
如果一个应用程序，因为意外或恶意传递错误参数给操作系统，
and the operating system would crash,
而导致操作系统崩溃，
that basically means for denial servers for every other application.
这意味着拒绝服务所有其他应用程序。
So the operating system has to be written in a way
所以操作系统必须以一种方式编写，
that it can deal and handle malicious applications.
让它可以处理恶意应用程序。
In particular, another concern is that the application should not be able cannot break out of its isolation,
特别是，另一个要考虑是应用程序不能打破它的隔离。
the application might be definitely malicious, maybe written by an attacker
应用程序可能完全是恶意的，或许由攻击者编写的，
and the attacker probably would like to break out of the application for example and take control over the kernel,
攻击者可以想打破应用程序，获得内核控制权，
and once you have control over the kernel, then you can do anything,
一旦控制了内核，你就可以做任何事情，
because the kernel is in control of all the hardware resources.
因为内核控制着所有硬件资源。
And so the operating system has to be able to [], has to be written defensively,
所以操作系统必须编写成防御性的，
you know to avoid those kinds of things.
防止出现这种事情。
This turns out to be very tricky to actually get right,
实现这个目标是很有技巧的，
you know, in fact in Linux, you know they're still periodic bugs,
实际上，在 Linux 中，仍然有偶发的 bug ，
you know kernel bugs or bugs that actually allow an applications exploited or to break out of this isolation domain and take control.
内核 bug ，这些 bug 允许应用程序打破隔离，并获得控制权。
But it's just a continuous concern and we'd like to do a good job as possible.
但是这是一个持续性的问题，我们要尽可能的做好这项工作。
And this is the mindset you have to have, when you're developing a kernel,
这就是你开发内核时要有的思维模式，
that actually applications are perhaps malicious.
实际的应用程序可能是恶意的。
You know, this means that means it has to be strong isolation between the apps and OS.
这意味着在应用程序和操作系统之间必须有强隔离。
If the OS you know need to be defensive and needs to be in a position that can be defensive,
如果操作系统需要是防御性的，需要处于可防御的位置，
there has to be a strong wall between the applications,
在应用程序之间必须有一道坚固的屏障，
so that the operating system can actually enforce whatever policies it wants to enforce.
让操作系统可以真正执行它想执行的任何策略。
And this is typically done, the typical approach to achieving this strong isolation is using hardware support.
这通常，实现强隔离的常用方法是硬件支持。
And we get a little bit of flavor of that in this lecture,
在这节课中，我们稍微了解一下，
but we'll come back to it in much more detail in subsequent lectures.
但是我们在后面的课程中会深入更多细节。
And two, two parts of the hardware support,
有两种方式的硬件支持，
one is something that's called user kernel mode, slash kernel mode,
一种称为用户内核模式， /kernel 模式，
in RISC-V is called supervised mode, but it's the same thing.
在 RISC-V 中称为管理者模式，但是是一种东西。
And then page tables, virtual memory.
另一种是页表，虚拟内存。
So all processors, sort of all series processors, that are intended to run an operating system multiple applications
所有处理器，想要运行多应用程序操作系统的处理器，
have support for user kernel mode and virtual memory,
都支持用户内核模式和虚拟内存，
you know it might be manifested were implemented in a slightly different ways,
它可能表现或实现有些许不同，
but basically all processors have it.
但是基本上所有处理器都有它。
And our RISC-V processor that we're using in this class has that support too.
我们在课程中使用的 RISC-V 处理器也有支持。
So let me talk a little bit,
所以，我来讲一下，
I'm going to talk a little bit about user mode, kernel mode first
我会先讲一下用户模式，内核模式，
and then we'll talk a little bit about virtual memory,
然后讲一下虚拟内存。
and mostly at the highest level possible,
主要从宏观角度，
because there's a lot of important details,
因为这里面有很多重要的细节，
but I won't be able to cover those in this lecture.
但这节课并不能包含这些。
So let's first talk about user kernel mode,
我们先来讨论一下用户内核模式，
and basically what it means is that the processor has two modes of operation
基本上就是处理器有两种操作模式，
and one is user mode and the other one is kernel mode.
一种是用户模式，另一种是内核模式。
And when running in kernel mode, the CPU can execute privileged instructions,
当运行在内核模式， CPU 可以执行特权指令，
[] back to the second [].
[]回到第二[]。
When running in user mode, CPU can only execute in unprivileged instructions.
当运行在用户模式， CPU 只能执行非特权指令。
And unprivileged instructions, the instructions you're well familiar with,
非特权指令，你已经很熟悉了，
you know, think about like add sub, adding two two registers together, you know subtracting two register,
比如 add sub ，对两个寄存器做加法或减法，
so it's really [basic], you know procedure calls you know jr, all that kind of stuff branches,
所以这是很普通的，还有程序调用 jr ，所有分支指令，
those are all unprivileged instructions, that any user application is allowed to execute.
这些都是非特权指令，任何用户程序都可以执行。
Privileged instructions are instructions that basically are involved in manipulating the hardware directly,
特权指令是引入直接操作硬件的指令，
you know setting up protections and things like that,
设置保护或类似的东西，
so for example setting up a page table register, which we'll talk about later,
比如配置页表寄存器，我们后面会谈到，
or, you know setting the disabling clock interrupts.
或者设置禁止时钟中断。
So there are all kinds of sort of state on the processor,
所以，处理器中有各种类型的状态，
that the operating system intended to use and manipulating that state
操作系统使用操作这些状态，
you know completely done, for privileged instructions.
都是由特权指令完成的。
And so, for example when a user application tries to actually execute a privilege instruction,
所以当用户程序试图执行特权指令，
then the processor rules won't execute, because if privileged instruction in user mode is disallowed
处理器规则不会执行，因为特权指令在用户模式下是不允许的，
and basically that will result in the transfer control from user space from user mode to kernel mode,
这会引起控制从用户模式到内核模式，
so that then the operating system can actually take control
让操作系统获得控制权，
and maybe [] kill the application because of misbehaving.
如果应用程序有问题，就可以杀掉它。
To get a little bit of sense, the difference between the two and privileged and unprivileged instructions,
为了进一步理解特权指令和非特权指令的不同，
let me switch display for second.
让我切换一下显示内容。
And here on the right side, you have a display is a document, you know the RISC-V privileged architecture document
这里右边显示的是一个文档， RISC-V 特权架构文档，
and that document contains all the privileged instructions,
这个文档包含所有特权指令，
it's linked from the website, under the References page
在网站（6.S081 课程主页）的 References 页面有它的链接，
and in the next couple of weeks or almost months,
在接下来的几周或几乎一个月内，
you know, you will be playing around you know all these privileged instructions, that you know are shown here
你会用到这里看到的所有特权指令，
and in fact many of them will show up and some of them [want] to show up in the next lecture in the great amount of detail.
事实上，它们中的大多数会在下节课中出现，包含大量细节。
But usually think about this as
可以这样想，
there are privileged instructions that user applications should not be able to execute
用户程序不能执行特权指令，
and those can only be executed in kernel mode.
它们指令在内核模式下执行。
So that's one aspect of you know this sort of hardware support for strong isolation.
所以，这是硬件支持强隔离的一个方面。
Yeah, Amanda, go ahead.
好的， Amanda ，请继续。
Just a quick question,
一个小问题，
like, the what I'm imagining in my head is something like if kernel mode allow else don't,
比如我想的是如果内核模式允许或不允许，
like what, who is running that code and checking if it's kernel mode
那么谁运行的检查代码，判断是否是内核模式，
and how do they know if it's in kernel mode, like a flag or something?
它们如何知道处于内核模式，是有一个标志或者其他东西吗？
Yeah, so basically flag in the processor,
是的，一般在处理器中有一个标志，
literally there's a bit in the processor, that's just you know user mode you know one is saying,
在处理器中有一个标志位，用户模式使用 1 ，
typically one is usual mode, zero is kernel mode.
一般 1 是用户模式， 0 是内核模式。
And so when the processor decodes an instruction, looks at the opcode
所以当处理器解码指令时，检查操作码，
if the opcode is a privilege instruction and the bit is set to one and will deny executing that instruction.
如果操作码是特权指令，并且那个位设置为 1 ，就会拒绝指定该指令。
You know divided by zero, you're not allowed to do that.
比如除零指令，就不允许执行。
Okay but if that bit has changed in some way
好的，但是如果那一位以某种方式改变，
you were just able to overwrite that bit then that's the only thing controlling.
就可以覆盖用来控制的那一位。
Yeah, so what do you think what instruction that overwrites a bit
是的，你认为可以覆盖那一位的指令，
is that a privileged instruction or unprivileged instruction.
它是特权指令还是非特权指令。
Is there a question.
有什么问题吗。
Clearly the instruction sets the bit must be privileged instruction,
设置那一位的指令当然是特权指令，
because the user application should not be able to set the bit to kernel mode, correct
因为用户程序不允许把那一位设置为内核模式，
and then be able to actually run all kinds of privileged instructions,
让它能够执行所有特权指令。
and so that bit is protected.
所以那一位是受保护的。
Does that make sense?
理解了吗？
Okay, yeah.
好的，是的。
Okay good,
好的，
so, so that's user kernel mode or at least the top view user kernel mode,
这就是用户内核模式，或者宏观的用户内核模式，
turns out to RISC-V has a number of, you asked about, have a third mode called machine mode,
RISC-V 还有第三种模式，就是你们问到的，称为机器模式，
we're we're mostly going to ignore that
我们可以忽略它，
and so I'm not going say about it,
我不准备讲它，
basically has one more level, because basically three levels of privilege instead of two levels of privileges.
就是多了一级，有三级特权而不是两级。
Amir, go ahead.
Amir ，继续。
Alright, so I'm wondering with respect to security,
好的，我想知道关于安全方面，
if all user code does go through the kernel, the intent is that things are secure,
如果所有用户代码通过内核，目的是为了安全，
but is there a way,
但是有没有一种方式，
for a user of the computer to completely go around the operating system.
计算机的用户可以完全绕过操作系统。
No, not really, at least if done carefully, not,
不，不是，至少如果做的很小心，不会出现，
and if possible, you know that might be the case,
如果可能，出现一种情况，
that some programs have additional privileges that the operating system will respect,
一些程序具有过多的操作系统相关的权限，
but those privileges are not given to every user
但是这些权限没有给每个用户，
you know only root user has certain privileges,
只有 root 用户拥有特定权限，
that allow you to do security sensitive operations.
可以执行对安全敏感的操作。
What about BIOS, does BIOS happened before OS or after.
那么 BIOS 呢， BIOS 是发生在操作系统之前还是之后。
Yeah, so the BIOS, this is a piece of software that basically comes with the computer,
是的， BIOS 是同计算机一起的一个软件，
and that's booted first and the BIOS basically boots the operating system,
它首先启动，并启动操作系统，
so the BIOS is a trusted piece of code, and better be correct and better be not malicious.
所以 BIOS 是一段可信任的代码，是正确的，没有恶意的。
Noah, go ahead.
Noah ，继续。
Yeah, so you mentioned that the, you know the instruction to set the the kernel mode bit is a privileged instruction,
是的，你提到设置内核模式标志位的指令是特权指令，
how would a user program ever, then be able to, you know get like you know essentially have the kernel, execute any kernel instructions,
那么用户程序怎么能，让内核执行任何内核指令，
if like the very instructions to access kernel mode is itself a privileged instruction,
比如获得内核模式的指令就是一个特权指令，
I guess it seems like there's immediately a [] for user program ever changing that bit.
我猜应该有一个直接的[]让用户可以修改那个位。
Yeah, yeah that's correct and that's exactly the way we want, that's correct,
是的，这是正确的，这就是我们想要的方式，
so one way to think about it, and this is not exactly how it works on the RISC-V,
所以可以这样考虑，虽然不完全是 RISC-V 的工作方式，
but if you execute a privilege instruction in user space will try to execute a privileged the instruction u-.
但是如果你在用户空间执行特权指令，试着执行特权指令……
I'm back, sorry about that, look like my zoom client crashed on me.
我回来了，不好意思，我的 zoom 客户端崩溃了。
I apologize for that I don't really know why, but it did.
抱歉，我也不知道怎么回事，但是发生了。
Can everybody hear me again.
大家能听到我说话吗。
Yep, you're good.
是的，好的。
All good.
好的。
Well there's somewhere a bug.
好的，某个地方有个 bug 。
Okay, back to, back to a second piece of hardware support
好的，回到硬件支持的第二部分，
and which almost all CPU provide witch CPUs provide virtual memory.
几乎所有 CPU 都提供了， CPU 提供的虚拟内存。
I'm going to talk about this on Wednesday in much more detail,
周三我会讲到更多细节，
but basically the processor have something you know what it's called a page table.
但是基本上，处理器有一个叫做页表的东西。
And you've seen this a little bit I think 6.004,
你们应该已经在 6.004 中看到了，
the page table, basically maps virtual addresses to physical addresses.
页表就是将虚拟地址映射到物理地址。
And the basic idea is to give every process its own page table.
基本思想是给每个进程提供自己的页表。
In this way, you know the, the process can actually only use
使用这种方式，进程只能使用，
whereas only allowed to access that piece of physical memory that actually shows up in its page table
只能访问它的页表中显示的物理内存，
and so if you set up if the operating system sets the page tables up in a way that every process has disjoint physical memory,
如果操作系统设置每个进程使用不相交的物理内存，
then a process can't even access somebody else's physical memory,
那么进程甚至不能访问其他进程的物理内存，
because it's not even in it's page tables,
因为那些（地址）甚至不在它的页表中，
so there's no way even to create an address or write down an address
所以，不能创建或写一个地址，
that will allow a process to access somebody else's physical memory.
允许进程访问其他进程的物理内存。
And so this gives a strong memory isolation.
所以，这提供了强内存隔离。
Basically page table defines view on memory,
页表定义了内存布局，
and every application, every user process has its own view of memory, independent of each other.
每个应用程序，每个用户进程有自己的内存布局，相互独立。
And this gives us very strong memory isolation.
这提供了很强的内存隔离。
And so now what we can do,
所以现在我们可以做，
if we can think a little bit in this way,
如果我们用这种方式思考，
then we can redraw the picture a little bit earlier
那么我们可以重新画出之前的这张图，
and because we're thinking about these as follows,
因为我们这样思考，
you have the box, and ls sits in that box
你有一个盒子， ls 在它里面，
and we have another box, you know, echo sits in that box,
我们有另一个盒子，而 echo 在这个盒子里，
in a box basically has an address virtual address
每个盒子包含地址，虚拟地址，
range starting from zero to whatever some number two to the power whatever the number is,
从 0 到某个数值， 2 的多少次方，
in RISC-V which we'll talk about on Wednesday.
在 RISC-V 中，我们将在周三讨论。
And similarly you know the address range for echo is to know something wherever same two to power x.
同样地， echo 的地址范围也是到 2^x 。
And so ls has memory location zero, echo has a location like zero,
所以 ls 有内存位置 0 ， echo 也有位置 0 ，
and usually completely separated,
通常是完全分开的，
and if the operating system maps those virtual addresses zero to different pieces of physical addresses,
如果操作系统将虚拟地址 0 映射到不同部分的物理内存，
then basically ls cannot access echo's memory and echo cannot access ls's memory.
那么 ls 不能访问 echo 的内存， echo 也不能访问 ls 的内存。
And similarly the kernel actually you know sits below it,
类似地，内核位于下方，
it also has his own at least in xv6 has his own address range, independent of the applications.
它也有自己的，至少在 xv6 中，有自己的地址范围，独立于应用程序。
And we could think about the user kernel mode, sort of sitting in between you know the boundary,
我们可以考虑用户内核模式，它位于边界之间，
you know things that actually run in user space running user mode,
在用户空间运行的东西运行在用户模式，
and things that sit in the kernel running kernel mode.
位于内核的东西运行在内核模式。
And that's sort of the picture that you should actually know OS, you know sits there, you know sitting in kernel mode,
这种图中，你应该知道操作系统位于内核模式，
so this is the picture should happen in your head.
所以，这张图片应该出现在你的脑海中。
Now, as described so far this picture is a little bit too strict,
到目前为止，这张图片有点太严格了，
you know we have basically put everything in a box,
我们把所有东西都放在一个盒子里，
but there's no way for one box to transfer control to another box.
但是没有办法使控制权从一个盒子转移到另一个盒子。
Clearly, that needs to happen,
当然，我们需要它发生，
because for example ls, you know probably wants to call you know read read system call or write system call,
因为，比如 ls 可以想要调用 read 系统调用或 write 系统调用，
or maybe you know whatever the shell want to call fork or exec
或者 shell 想要调用 fork 或 exec ，
and so there has to be way for an application or user application to transfer control in a coordinated manner to the kernel,
所以需要一种方法，让应用程序以协调的方式将控制权转移到内核，
so the kernel can actually provide services.
让内核可以提供服务。
And so, there's a plan,
所以，有一种方案，
basically in addition to this, two pieces of hardware support, I talked so far, talked about so far,
除了我之前讨论过的这两种硬件支持，
is a way of controlled way of entering the kernel.
有一种控制方法进入内核。
It turns out actually RISV-V there is an instruction, for this, it's called the ecall instruction.
在 RISC-V 中，有一个这样的指令，称为 ecall 指令。
And ecall instruction, it takes one argument a number,
ecall 指令接受一个参数，一个数字，
and so when a user application that wants to transfer control into the kernel,
所以当用户程序想要将控制权转移到内核，
basically call the ecall instruction with numbers like two or three or four five
调用 ecall 指令，使用数字，比如 2 3 4 5 ，
and that number basically is the system call number that the application wants to invoke.
这个数字就是应用程序想要访问的系统调用编号。
And then basically what that does
这个指令做的是，
and actually enters the kernel at a particular point, a particular location in the ker-, in the kernel that's controlled by the kernel,
进入内核中的一个由内核控制的特定位置，
as we'll see you in xv6 in some later lectures.
我们会在后面的一些课程中在 xv6 中看到。
You know there's basically a single system call entry point,
有一个单独的系统调用入口位置，
and, and every time an application calls ecall and the application enters the kernel that particular point.
每次应用程序调用 ecall ，应用程序进入内核的特定位置。
So, one, so one way to think about this is that
所以，一种思考方式是，
if you have fork, you know fork, you know call in user space,
如果你调用 fork ，在用户空间调用 fork ，
for example the shell or your prime program called fork,
比如 shell 或 prime 程序调用 fork ，
well whatever calls fork, doesn't really call the operating system directly, the corresponding function in the kernel,
不论什么调用 fork ，实际上没有直接调用操作系统内核对应的函数，
instead you know what it does it actually calls the ecall with you know the number for fork,
而是调用 ecall ，使用 fork 的系统调用编号，
and then that actually jumps into the kernel.
然后进入内核。
So this is a kernel transition,
所以这是一次内核转换，
and here's the user side, here's a kernel side
这是用户侧，这是内核侧，
and then on the kernel site, you know there's a function called syscall in syscall.c
在内核侧，有一个函数 syscall 在 syscall.c 中，
and then basically every system call will end up at that particular system call function
每次系统调用都会到这个特定的系统调用函数，
and the system call will look at the number and then decide and the number actually passed in register, I think it's a0,
系统调用查找数字，然后决定传递给寄存器 a0 的数字，
and system call look at that register look at a0, see what the number is
系统调用查找那个寄存器 a0 ，查看是哪个数字，
and then for example called the fork system call.
然后调用比如 fork 系统调用。
And so just to make clear,
为了理解清楚，
so this is this hard boundary between the user and kernel,
这里是用户和内核的硬边界，
so the user cannot call you know this fork directly,
用户不能直接调用这个 fork ，
you know the only way user application can actually invoke this system call fork is actually through the ecall instruction.
用户程序调用 fork 的唯一方法是通过 ecall 指令。
And so we have another, if we have another another system call, let's say write,
所以我们有另一个，有另一个系统调用，比如 write ，
it does something similar, you know the write system called cannot call you know the write you know code directly into the kernel,
它也是类似的， write 系统调用不能直接调用内核中的 write 代码，
instead, what it does, it calls what's these little wrappers are called,
而是调用包装函数，
system call [stops] and will call ecall
系统调用[停止]并调用 ecall ，
and function called write that actually executes ecall instruction with the argument you know sys_write to indicate the write system call
函数 write ，执行 ecall 指令使用参数 sys_write ，表示 write 系统调用，
and again transfer control to syscall and then syscall can actually demultiplex into the write system call.
将控制权给 syscall ，然后 syscall 可以分配到 write 系统调用。
There are two questions, please go ahead.
这里有两个问题，请继续（提问）。
So I think my hands up both.
我想我们都举手了。
Okay, I can go ahead.
好的，我可以先提问。
Oh, the question I had was, how does or where does the kernel check,
我的问题是，怎样或在哪里检查，
for, for example fork or write, if it is allowed or not,
比如 fork 或 write ，它们是否允许，
right now, you're just passing in like you know you're just calling ecall and the system call number,
目前，你只是调用 ecall ，使用系统调用编号，
but where does the kernel basically decide whether this application should be able to invoke this particular kernel syscall.
但是内核在哪里决定程序可以调用特定的内核系统调用。
Yeah, so a great question,
是的，这是个好问题，
so in principle you know on the kernel side correct when we actually fork call runs,
理论上，在内核侧，我们真正运行 fork 的这边，
it can implement any secure check it wants,
它可以实现任何想要的安全检查，
you could look at the arguments in the system call
可以检查系统调用的参数，
and decide whether actually the application should be allowed to execute the system call fork,
决定应用程序是否允许执行系统调用 fork ，
now in user in Unix, any application can actually call fork,
在 Unix 中，任何应用程序都可以调用 fork ，
but let's say take write, you know write,
让我们来讨论 write ，
you need to check whether, the implantation of write needs to check whether the address that is actually passed into write actually is part of the user applications,
write 需要检查，传给 write 的地址是否属于应用程序，
and so that you know the kernel is not correct to writing a data from somewhere else it actually doesn't belong to the application,
内核不能写数据到不属于该应用程序的地方，
There more hints, you know, please ask.
还有更多线索，请提问。
Yeah I had a quick question,
是的，我有一个问题，
so how did the kernel seize back control from a user application,
内核如何夺回从用户程序夺回控制权，
in the case where the user application is acting maliciously or in an infinite loop.
在用户程序是恶意的或处于无限循环的情况下。
Yeah, so the way the plan for that
是的，这种情况的方法是，
and again we're going to talk about in much more detail in a couple weeks,
我们会在后面几周讨论更多的细节，
is that the kernel actually programs the hardware to set a timer,
方法是内核对硬件编程设置一个定时器，
and after the timer goes off, that will cause a transfer from user space to kernel mode,
在定时器结束后，会触发从用户空间切换到内核模式，
at that point the kernel is back in control
在这个时间点，内核重新获得控制权，
and then the kernel can reschedule the CPU to another process.
然后内核可以重新调度 CPU 给其他进程。
Okay make sense, thank you.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Yeah, we'll see the exact details you know we'll see a little while.
是的，我们会在一段时间之后看到具体细节。
You have more questions?
还有问题吗？
Yeah, so this is more of a high-level question,
是的，有一个高层次的问题，
but what drives the designers of an operating systems implementation to use a language like C.
为什么设计者使用 C 语言来实现操作系统。
Um, okay, so great question,
好的，好问题，
C gives you a lot of control over hardware
C 语音给了你控制硬件的能力，
and so for example, you know you need to program the timer chip
比如，你可以对定时器编程，
and in C that is actually easy to do,
在 C 语言中，很容易做到，
because you get a lot of low-level control over any hardware resource
因为你可以控制任何硬件资源，
and partly because you can cast anything to anything,
部分原因是你可以转换任何东西，
and, so C is basically very convenient programming language,
所以， C 语言是非常方便的编程语言，
if you have to move very low-level programming particularly interacting with hardware.
如果你需要底层编程，特别是与硬件交互。
It doesn't mean you can't do it in other languages,
这并不意味着你不能使用别的语言，
but this is historically the reason why C has been successful.
但这是历史上 C 语言成功的原因。
I see, thanks.
我明白了，谢谢。
Why C so much more popular than C plus plus only for historic reasons,
为什么 C 比 C++ 更流行，仅仅是历史原因吗，
in like these kinds of applications
比如那些应用程序，
or is there any other reason that like, no like most of OS don't have adopted C plus plus.
或者其他原因，比如大多数操作系统没有采用 C++ 。
Yeah, so most operating system,
是的，大多数操作系统，
there are I think operating systems written in C plus plus totally possible,
我相信使用 C++ 编写操作系统是完全可能的，
probably the most ones that you know you know are not written in C plus plus,
可能大多数不是使用 C++ 编写，
and the very reason for you know Linux is mostly C or no C plus plus,
Linux 使用 C 而不是 C++ 的原因，
I think partially because Linus just doesn't like C plus plus.
我想部分是因为 Linus 不喜欢 C++ 。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay so, so in this view of the world,
好的，所以在这个角度来看，
were you know we have a way of transferring control into the operating system using system calls or ecall instruction
我们有一种方式将控制权转移到内核，使用系统调用，使用 ecall 指令，
and the kernel is now responsible for implementing actually the actual functions
内核负责实现真正的函数，
and ensuring checking arguments and things like that
确保检查参数或类似的事情，
to make sure that you know that it's not being tricked or something, doing something badly
保证不会被骗而做一些坏事，
and so in this view of the world the kernel is sometimes called you know, it's the trusted computing base,
从这种角度看，内核有时候称为可信任计算基础，
sometimes called in security terms the TCB.
有时在安全术语中称为 TCB 。
And basically you know what does it mean to be the trusted computing base, well it must be correct, kernel must have no bug.
可信任计算基础意思是，它必须正确，必须没有 bug 。
Because if there's a bug in the kernel,
因为如果内核中有 bug ，
you know the way to think about this stuff,
需要考虑这种方式，
maybe an attacker is able to to take the bug and turn the bug into an exploit.
可能攻击者会利用那个 bug ，使 bug 变成一个漏洞。
And you know that exploit may be allowed particular attacker to break out of isolation or maybe take control over the kernel.
那个漏洞可能允许特定攻击者打破隔离，或者控制内核。
And so it's really important that you know the kernel really, it has to have as few bugs as possible.
这很重要，内核必须尽可能没有 bug 。
Basically the kernel, you must treat, must treat user apps, application of processes as malicious.
内核必须将用户程序当成是恶意的。
Basically as I said before, [] the kernel designer should have a security mindset,
就像我之前说的，内核设计者必须有安全思维模式，
you know when writing and implementing kernel code.
在编写和实现内核代码的时候。
In in its heart to achieve this goal is have no bugs,
达成这个目标的关键是没有 bug ，
if the operating system gigantic and big, it's not that straightforward
如果操作系统非常庞大，那不是那么简单的，
and almost every operating system, you know the user is widely used,
几乎所有操作系统，用户广泛使用的，
once in a while actually has a security bug and they get fixed over time,
有时也会有安全性 bug ，它们随着时间得到修复，
but basically no matter what, there's always a new exploit at some point down the line
但是不论怎样，总会在某个时刻出现新的漏洞，
and you will see later why it's so tricky to get it all at right,
后面你会看到为什么保证所有东西正确是如此困难，
but you know the sort of understandable like in the kernel has to do tricky stuff,
但是，你要理解内核必须做这些困难的事情，
it has to manipulate hardware, it has to be very careful in it's checking,
它要操作硬件，而且必须很小心地检查，
it's very easy to make a small slip up and you know have a bug.
很容易犯一个小错误，造成出现 bug 。
And so, an instant question is then what should run in kernel mode,
所以一个显而易见的问题是，什么应该运行在内核模式，
because it's really the kernel code actually is in kernel mode that is the sensitive code right, that is the trusted computing base.
因为在内核模式中的内核代码是敏感代码，是可信任计算基础。
And one answer to that question is
这个问题的一种答案是，
like, well you know we have our user kernel boundary, so here's user, here's kernel,
我们有用户内核边界，这边是用户，这边是内核，
and user applications running, and here is the program running in kernel mode,
用户程序运行，而这里是运行在内核模式的程序，
one option is to stick the whole operating system in kernel mode,
一种选择是将整个操作系统置于内核模式，
for example, in most Unix operating systems, the whole Unix implementation runs inside of kernel mode.
比如，在大多数 Unix 操作系统中，整个 Unix 实现运行在内核模式。
So you have in xv6, all the operating system services are basically in kernel mode,
在 xv6 中，所有操作系统服务都在内核模式，
and this is called monolithic kernel design.
这被称为宏内核设计。
And you know there, there's a couple things are the way to think about it,
可以从几方面考虑这个设计，
one it's probably not so good for bugs, right,
一方面它可能对减少 bug 不友好，
because any bug you know that you might have in monolithic design, might actually turn into an exploit and that would be bad,
因为任何宏内核设计的 bug 可能成为漏洞，这是不好的，
so we have a large operating system running inside of the kernel,
我们有一个很大的操作系统在内核中，
it's likely they're going to be more bugs,
可能会有更多 bug ，
but any statistics that could look up it says like every few thousand lines of code will have you know some small number of bugs,
统计数据表明每千行代码都会有一些 bug ，
and so if you have many, many more lines of code running in the kernel block,
所以如果你有很多行代码在内核中，
you know the probability the chance that you have and the serious bug goes up a little bit
出现严重 bug 的可能性就会变高，
and so downside for monolithic kernel design from security perspective is there's a lot of code in the kernel.
所以宏内核设计的缺点是，从安全角度来说，有很多代码在内核中。
The plus though is
好的方面是，
you know typically if you think about an operating system contains all kinds of different pieces,
操作系统包含所有不同的部分，
you know you might have file system piece, you might have the virtual memory piece, you might have processes
可能包含文件系统，可能包含虚拟内存，可能包含进程，
and so there are all kinds of sub modules inside of the operating system that implement particular functionality.
在操作系统中有实现特定功能的不同的子模块。
And the plus side of that is there's going to be tight integration, possible between these different sub modules,
好的方面是，这些不同的子模块可以紧密结合，
if they're all sitting in the same program and that connection leads to great performance.
它们都在一个程序中，这种联系会带来很好的性能。
An example, if you look at operating system Linux, it actually achieves a very impressive performance.
举个例子，如果你查看 Linux 操作系统，它达到了很好的性能。
And so there's one, one design, another design
还有另外一种设计，
which basically focuses on reducing the amount of code in the kernel is what's called micro kernel design.
主要目标是减少内核中的代码，就是所谓的微内核设计。
And in this design, your goal is actually to run as fewer lines as possible in kernel mode
在这种设计中，目标是在内核模式中运行尽量少的代码，
and for example there is something in kernel,
比如，有一些东西在内核中，
but the kernel has very few components in it,
但是内核中包含很少的组件，
so general typically has some form of IPC or message passing,
一般包含某种形式的 IPC 或消息传递，
a little bit of VM support very minimal, basically, only thing necessary for page tables
少量的虚拟内存支持，基本上，只有页表相关的东西，
and something to multiplex different CPUs, so some multiplexing code.
一些复用不同 CPU 的东西，复用代码。
But generally the goal is to run the bug of the opening system outside of the kernel.
但是通常的目标是使操作系统 bug 处于内核之外。
And so for example again, as we have our boundary here,
比如，我们在这里有边界，
what we'll do is actually we'll run other parts of the kernel as user normal user applications,
我们要做的是把内核的其他部分当作普通用户程序，
for example you might have, you might have a user process,
比如，你可能有一个用户进程，
but still it's not intended, but doesn't matter,
不是我想要的（颜色），但没关系，
you know what I just did file server,
我做的是文件服务器，
and so and then the file server is just in regular user space,
文件服务器只是在普通用户空间，
user space, kernel,
用户空间，内核，
so even though I drew a by accident in red, I intended to draw in black,
尽管我意外使用了红色来画图，我希望是使用黑色，
the file system might running a user application like echo, you know the shell,
文件系统就像用户程序，比如 echo shell ，
they're all run in user space
它们都运行在用户空间，
and we might have other user applications
我们可能有其他的用户程序，
like parts of the VM system might actually run the regular user application in user mode.
比如部分虚拟内存系统在用户模式运行普通用户程序。
And so this is sort of a nice design correct,
所以这是一种不错的设计，
because the amount of code that presumably that's in the kernel is small.
因为内核中的代码量可能很少。
It's small and small means, hopefully fewer bugs.
很少意味着更少的 bug 。
The one issue, of course like we have to arrange that the shell can talk to the file system,
一个问题是，当然我们需要安排 shell 可以访问文件系统，
for example, the shell calls exec and there has to be a way of getting to the file system
比如， shell 调用 exec ，必许有一种方式访问文件系统，
and so typically the way that works is that the shell will send a message through the IPC system to the kernel,
通常工作方式是， shell 通过 IPC 系统发送一个消息给内核，
the kernel will look at it and say like oh you know this is intended for the file system, so the file system sent to the file system,
内核查看，知道需要访问文件系统，发送给文件系统，
the file system does for work, you know sends a message back
文件系统工作，返回一条消息，
saying you know, here's the results of your exec system call
表明这是 exec 系统调用的结果，
and then you know send it back to the shell.
然会发回给 shell 。
And so, these are typically implemented using messages,
所以，这通常是使用消息实现的，
and so for any interaction with the file server,
所以对于任何与文件服务的交互，
now you have to jump once into the kernel, once out of the kernel, once into the kernel, once out of the kernel.
现在必须跳入内核，跳出内核，再跳入内核，再跳出内核。
If you compare that with the previous design,
与前面的设计比较，
like if this guy wants to talk to the file system, it's one system call in and one basically call back out.
访问文件系统，有一次系统调用跳入，一次跳出。
So you double the number of system called entries.
所以系统调用次数翻了一番。
And so one typical problem or challenge which offers the micro kernel approaches is actually how to achieve good performance.
所以微内核方式的一个典型的问题或挑战是如何获得高性能。
And they have sort of two components to it,
它由两部分组成，
one you know just jumping back and forth between user mode and kernel mode to actually get something done
一个是在用户模式和内核之间来回切换来完成事情，
and the second part is because you know the different pieces are really well isolated from each other, a tight integration is less,
第二是，因为不同的部分彼此隔离，没有紧密结合，
you know, more complicated to arrange than,
使得安排更复杂，
for example in the monolithic kernel where basically everybody can
比如在宏内核中，每个部分都可以，
for example the file system the virtual memory system can easily share a page cache,
比如文件系统，虚拟内存系统可以很容易地共享页缓存，
which a little bit harder to achieve in the micro kernel design
这在微内核设计中是比较难的，
and therefore it's sometimes more difficult to get high performance.
因此，有时它更难获得高性能。
Now these distinctions between micro and monolithic very high-level,
这些是微内核和宏内核高层次的区别，
so in practice both types of kernel designs show up,
在实践中，两种内核设计都有应用，
most desktop operating systems are typically monolithic systems, mostly for historical reasons.
因为历史原因，大多数桌面操作系统是宏内核系统。
A lot of the if you run very intense you know OS intense applications
很多，如果你运行密集型，操作系统密集型应用程序，
for example in the data center, they typically run on a monolithic kernel,
比如数据中心，它们一般运行在宏内核，
mostly because for example Linux provides great performance,
主要是因为 Linux 提供了良好的性能，
but many for example embedded [systems] like Minix or seL4,
但是很多嵌入式系统比如 Minix 或 seL4 ，
those all tend to be a micro kernel designs.
它们往往是微内核设计。
And so both designs are popular,
两种设计都很流行，
you could probably start a new operation system from scratch,
你可以从头开始设计一个新的操作系统，
you probably start with, you know you may start with a micro kernel design.
你可以从一个微内核设计开始。
And once you have a monolithic design like for example Linux,
一旦你有一个像 Linux 的宏内核设计，
it's going to be would be a ton of work to rewrite anything to micro kernel design,
重写成微内核设计会有很多工作要做，
as maybe not conducive to the [incentives],
可能不利于[激励]，
people probably want to spend rather time implementing new features than actually restructuring the kernel.
人们更想花时间来增加新功能，而不是重新设计内核。
So, these are sort of two main designs,
这是两种主要的设计，
as you know xv6 is falls into monolithic design, is most classic Unix systems do,
如你所知， xv6 是宏内核设计，是经典 Unix 系统所采用的，
but later in the semester, we'll talk a lot more in detail about some of the micro kernel designs.
但是在本学期晚些时候，我们会讨论更多微内核设计的细节。
Any questions about this, because this was a hot topic in the, in the email questions.
还有什么问题吗，因为这是邮件问题中的热门话题。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, let me switch a little bit,
好的，让我转换一下，
I'm going to switch to some code and see how this plays out in xv6.
我会转到一些代码，看看这些在 xv6 中是如何运行的。
So here's two windows.
这里有两个窗口。
You know emacs, you know with like the proc structure,
在 emacs 窗口，是 proc 结构体，
and the first thing I wanna do is, you know look a little bit at the code base,
我首先做的是，查看一下代码库，
you've probably already done this,
你们可能已经做过了，
but you see that the code is organized around three in three parts, one to kernel.
你可以看到代码分为三个部分，一个是 kernel 。
And you know the kernel that basically includes all the kernel files,
kernel 包含了所有的内核文件，
xv6 being a monolithic kernel, basically all these programs are compiled into a single binary called the kernel
xv6 是宏内核，所有这些程序编译成一个二进制文件 kernel ，
and that's actually what you know run in kernel mode.
那就是运行在内核模式的部分。
And then you know there's user and those are basically the programs that run the user mode.
然后有 user 部分，这些就是运行在用户模式的程序。
And this is why, you know one is called kernel and the other called user.
这也是为什么一个叫做 kernel ，另一个叫做 user 。
And then there's one more program called mkfs,
然后，还有一个程序叫做 mkfs ，
which actually builds an empty file system image, you know that we are stored on disk,
它会构建一个空文件系统镜像，保存在磁盘上，
so that we can get off the ground with an empty file system.
让我们可以从一个空文件系统开始。
Okay, so before, so you know switch back again to,
好的，在继续之前，再次切换到，
I want to say a little bit about how the kernel is compiled.
我想说一下内核是如何编译的。
You've probably seen this, you might not really have realized it, it's important to understand.
你可能已经看到这个，没有注意它，但理解它是很重要的。
So when the kernel, the construction of the kernel,
所以当 kernel ， kernel 的结构，
the makefile basically takes one of these C files like proc.c,
makefile 选取 C 文件中的一个，比如 proc.c ，
you know invokes you know the GCC, the GCC compiler that generates a file called proc.S,
调用 GCC 编译器生成文件 proc.S ，
that goes through the assembler,
再通过汇编器，
and this is basically RISC-V assembly,
这个是 RISC-V 汇编代码，
and then actually produces a file proc.o and basically that's you know the binary version of the assembler,
然后产生一个文件 proc.o ，这是汇编程序的二进制版本，
and you know the makefile does this rule, you know part files in the kernel,
makefile 对 kernel 中的文件执行这个规则，
so for example pipe, another one you know, same story,
比如，另一个， pipe ，也是同样的流程，
GCC compiles to pipe.S, and you know go to through assembler and we get a pipe.o.
GCC 将其编译成 pipe.S ，再通过汇编器我们得到 pipe.o 。
And basically then the loader, it takes all these .o files, from all the different files
然后加载器使用所有不同文件生成的 .o 文件，
and links them together and produces produces a kernel,
将它们链接在一起，生成 kernel 。
and that was actually you know what we run.
就是我们要运行的东西。
And you know for your convenience, you know the makefile also produces a file called kernel.asm,
为了方便， makefile 也生成一个文件 kernel.asm ，
that has the complete kernel disassembled
它包含所有 kernel 反汇编代码，
and you can just look at it and you know that helps later on when you have kernel bugs
你可以查看它，在有内核 bug 的时候提供帮助，
and it's easy to see which instruction was executed to the point you got the bug.
可以很容易看到 bug 发生时的指令。
As an example if I, here kernel.asm, we see here's the kernel file assembly instructions.
比如，这是 kernel.asm ，我们可以看到这是内核汇编指令。
And one thing you know, for example is that the first instruction is located at this address eight zero zero zero zero zero
你需要知道一件事情，第一条指令位于地址 80000000 ，
and that is whatever auipc instruction RISC-V instruction.
它是 auipc 指令， RISC-V 指令。
And, anybody knows what this is,
有人知道这些是什么吗，
zero zero eight one one seven, or eight three one three, six five o five.
0000a117, 83010113, 6505 。
Anyone want to answer that question?
有人想回答这个问题吗？
That's the hex version of the assembly instructions on the right?
那是右边汇编指令的十六进制版本？
Yeah exactly,
是的，完全正确，
so what here on the zero zero eight one one seven is exactly the same thing as symbolic you know the textual version of that auipc
所以 0000a117 是与文本的 auipc 相同的东西，
and so basically this is the binary encoding of the actual instruction.
所以这是实际指令的二进制编码。
So, and every instruction has a binary encoding
所以，每个指令都有二进制编码，
and you know the kernel.asm file actually shows those binary encodings.
kernel.asm 文件显示了这些二进制编码。
And this is sometimes convenient,
这有时是很方便的，
when you look at GDB, and you want to know what actually is going on,
当你查看 GDB ，想知道实际发生了什么，
you can see actually the binary encoding is.
你就可以看到二进制编码。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so then when we run xv6, I'm going to run inside,
好的，当我们运行 xv6 ，我要运行，
actually let me first run it without GDB.
让我先在没有 GDB 的情况下运行。
You know compile a bunch of stuff and then invokes QEMU,
你知道编译很多东西，然后调用 QEMU 。
and this is a basically C program, that simulates or emulates RISC-V processor.
这是一个 C 程序，用来模拟 RISC-V 处理器。
You can see here in the dash kernel flag, actually passes the kernel,
你可以在这里看到 -kernel 标志，传递了内核，
and as a program can be run inside of QEMU
作为一个可以在 QEMU 中运行的程序，
and QEMU and the kernel agreed basically the starting place for any program is to address eight zero zero zero zero.
QEMU 和 内核约定任何程序的起始点是地址 80000000 。
And we see that we passed a couple of flags in QEMU,
我们可以看到我们传递了很多标志给 QEMU ，
it's just you know, m, that's an amount of memory that the machine this virtual machine has, this virtual RISC-V machine,
m ，是虚拟机拥有的内存量，这个 RISC-V 机器，
it passes in how many of cores there are a passes in the machine,
传递多少个 CPU 核，传递给这个机器，
the disk drive which contains the file fs.img.
磁盘包含文件 fs.img 。
And so basically a bunch of things are set up to make QEMU behaves like a real computer.
所以设置了很多东西让 QEMU 像一台真正的计算机。
And so one way when you think about QEMU,
所以你考虑 QEMU 的一种方式是，
really you should not think about it as a C program,
不要把它想成是一个 C 程序，
really the way you should think about it is as follows,
而是想成像下面这样，
you should think about it as as this, namely, a real board.
把它想成这个，一块真正的电路板。
So, for example there on the left you know this is a RISC-V board,
比如，左边这个是一块 RISC-V 电路板，
actually the RISC-V board that sits in my office
实际上，这块 RISC-V 电路板在我的办公室里，
and it can boot more or less xv6.
它可以启动 xv6 。
And so when you're running you know QEMU with your kernel,
所以当你在 QEMU 上运行你的内核，
you should think about it that actually running it on this board.
你应该想成是运行在这块板上。
And you know the board has been on off button,
这块板有开关按钮，
here's actually to RISC-V processor,
这里是 RISC-V 处理器，
you know there's room for peripherals, for example one of these connectors is a connector for Ethernet,
这里有外设空间，比如其中之一是以太网接口。
one is that PCIe slots,
一个是 PCIe 插槽，
there's some RAM chips on the board, I don't exactly know where they are, but there are.
板上有 RAM 芯片，我不知道在哪里，但确实有。
And so this is sort of, that's the physical hardware, the computer actually actually you're programming,
所以这是你编程的计算机硬件资源，
so xv6 managers this board, and that's the picture usually have in your head.
所以 xv6 管理这块板，这是你脑海中通常会有的图像。
And in fact if you zoom in, you can find all the documentation of what actually sits inside of this.
实际上，如果你放大，你可以找到内部的所有文档。
And inside of this, you know the inside of this RISC-V processor,
这个内部， RISC-V 处理器内部，
the schema for the RISC-V processor is shown in this picture here.
RISC-V 处理器结构显示在这张图片上。
And you know see here for example there are multiple cores, in fact, four cores,
这里可以看到有多个内核，实际上是四核，
you know there's a l2 cache,
有一个 l2 缓存，
there's a connector to DRAM,
有一个到 DRAM 的接口，
you know there's a bunch of ways to connect to the outside world,
有多种方式可以连接到外部世界，
so for example here UART0
比如，这个是 UART0 ，
and UART0 is actually connected on one end to the keyboard and to the other end to the display.
UART0 连接着，一端是键盘，另一端是显示器。
And you know there are some ways to actually clock's going,
这里有让时钟运行的方法，
I'll talk about in much more detail later,
后面我会讲到更多细节，
but these are all the components that basically you know the xv6 or things that you will be modifying to interact with the real hardware.
但是这些是 xv6 或你要修改的东西与真实硬件交互的组件。
And in fact the computer system or the computer board that actually is emulated by QEMU is pretty close,
事实上，计算机系统或计算机板与 QEMU 模拟的非常相似，
you know minus some small details to this particular computer board which is made by SiFive.
除了 SiFive 制造的电路板的上的一些小细节。
And unfortunately I can't tell you the real thing I just sit in my office,
遗憾的是，我不能坐在办公室里展示真实的东西，
you know and I haven't been in my office since March, probably collecting a lot of dust,
自从三月，我就没有去过我的办公室了，可能积了很多灰尘，
but it's important to keep in your head when you're running QEMU, you're running basically on real hardware.
但是记住这点很重要，当你运行 QEMU ，你就像运行在真正的硬件上。
And just happens to be able to software.
只是能够使用软件。
Does that make sense, [] sit in here.
能理解吗，这里的[]。
So let me say a little bit more about it,
让我来多讲一点，
so what does it mean for QEMU emulate the RISC-V processor.
QEMU 模拟 RISC-V 处理器是什么意思。
Well, literally you know if you think about it, you know as I said you know QEMU C program it's an open source C program,
如果你考虑它，像我说的， QEMU 是一个开源的 C 程序，
it's a big program, you can actually just download it or get clone it.
它是一个很大的程序，你可以下载或 clone 它。
But internally into C is basically for loop, an infinite for loop,
但是 C 代码内部是一个 for 循环，一个无限 for 循环，
that basically does nothing else than read instruction, RISC-V instruction basically reads four byte or eight bytes,
它只是读指令， RISC-V 指令，读取 4 或 8 个字节，
and basically looks at the bits in that instruction and decodes them, figures out what the opcode is.
检查指令的比特位并对其进行解码，弄清操作码是什么。
And we saw that for some of the instructions, the binary version of those instructions in the .asm file,
我们看到了一些指令，在 .asm 文件中的指令的二进制版本，
so decodes the instruction, so for example, maybe it will decide this is an add instruction, sub instruction, RISC-V sub instruction,
解码指令，比如这是一条 add 指令， sub 指令，
and then basically it executes the instruction in software.
然后它在软件中执行指令。
And you know that basically is all what it does, for every core, you know runs this particular loop.
这就是它所做的，在每个核心上运行这个循环。
In addition sort of doing, this loop have to maintain some states maintain state for all the registers.
除了做这些，这个循环还需要维护一些状态，维护所有寄存器状态。
So it has C decoration for like x0 register zero, x1 etc.
所以它有 C 风格的寄存器， x0 x1 等等。
And so basically when it executes instruction
所以当它执行指令时，
for example, the instruction is like whatever add you know a0 you know one to seven and storage in a0,
指令比如是 add a0, 1 到 7 ，然后存入 a0 ，
basically it takes a constant seven one, add them up and sticks into a0, for example stores seven in it.
它获取常数 7 和 1 ，把它们加起来并放入 a0 ，比如存入 7 。
And then executes the next instruction and it keeps going keeps going.
然后执行下一条指令，并继续执行。
In addition to basically emulating or [correctly] all the unprivileged instructions, it also emulates all the privileged instructions.
除了模拟所有非特权指令，它也模拟所有特权指令。
So that is in essence what QEMU does,
这就是 QEMU 实质上所做的，
the best picture for you to have your head is the basically you're running on a real physical RISC-V processor,
对你来说，脑海中最好的图像是运行在一个真正的 RISC-V 处理器上，
like the ones you have probably, you know many of you implemented [one] after the 6.004.
像你可能已经做过的，你们中许多人在 6.004 课程实现的那个。
Any questions about this?
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Um, hi, yeah I was wondering, if it does any hardware tricks, so like overlapping instructions or anything.
是的，我想知道，它有没有采用什么硬件技巧，比如指令重叠或其他的。
Um no, it runs on a real processor below it correct,
没有，它运行在一个真正的处理器上，
when you run QEMU, it runs probably on an x86 processor,
当你运行 QEMU ，它可能运行在 x86 处理器上，
that x86 processor does all kinds of tricks, to pipeline instructions and things like that right,
那个 x86 处理器做了所有技巧，指令流水线或其他的，
so the way to think about QEMU just a C program.
所以应该只是把 QEMU 当成一个 C 程序。
Makes sense, thank you.
理解了，谢谢。
What about multi threading,
那么关于多线程呢，
so if the the QEMU supports you said four cores or does it only support one
如果 QEMU 支持四核还是只支持一核，
and it's in that case, does it have actually multiple threads running it.
在这种情况下，它是否真正支持多线程。
Yeah, so actually the QEMU that we use on Athena, and were probably the ones that you actually download,
是的，我们在 Athena 上使用的或是你下载的 QEMU ，
they will use multiple threads internally, so QEMU internally use it to get parallelism,
它们内部会使用多线程， QEMU 使用它获得并行能力，
so in fact these four cores that are being emulated are being emulated in parallel.
实际上，模拟的四核就是并行模拟的。
And we'll see that in one of the labs later, how how that plays out.
我们将在后面的实验中看到，这是如何发挥作用的。
So definitely there's a real parallelism going on between the different cores.
所以，这些核心之间肯定是有真正的并行的。
Okay, so I'm gonna do a little bit of walking through xv6
好的，我会查看 xv6 ，
to get a little bit of sense what the layout of the [land] is,
来了解一下它的结构是什么样的，
in in later lecture again, we're gonna go in much more detail.
在后面的课程中，我们会知道更多细节。
So I'm going to fire up QEMU and with GDB supports,
所以我启动 QEMU ，并支持 GDB ，
basically QEMU has inside of a GDB server.
QEMU 内部支持 GDB 服务器。
And so it started up and then just wait, you know for GDB to connect to that.
它启动了，等待 GDB 连接。
I'm going to start here on my computer, this is a risc64-linux-gun-gdb.
在我的电脑上运行 risc64-linux-gnu-gdb 。
On some of your machines, might be multi-arch or something else,
在你们的电脑上，可能是 multi-arch 或其他东西，
but basically the GDB compiled for risc64, RISC-V 64.
但是是为 RISC-V 64 编译的 GDB 。
And I'm gonna set the break point at entry,
我在入口处设置断点，
because that's the first we know it has roughly the first instruction that actually working is going to jump to.
因为我们知道这是实际工作时跳到的第一条指令。
I set the break point, run
我设置断点并运行，
and basically doesn't actually break exactly at eight zero zero zero but zero a
不是准确地在 8000 处中断，而是在 0a 处，
and if we look here on the right,
我们查看右边，
you know we see that zero a is a right reading the control system register, mhartid and loading that value into a1.
看到 0a 是读取控制系统寄存器 mhartid ，并加载它的值到 a1 中。
And so basically QEMU simulates the instruction, then we can execute instruction, then we go to the next instruction.
所以 QEMU 模拟指令，执行指令，然后继续下一条指令。
In basically, this address eight zero zero zero it's just basically something that was agreed on, you know by QEMU or QEMU told,
这个地址 8000 就是一个 QEMU 指定的地址，
you know basically says, you want to use QEMU, the first instruction we're going to jump to is at that particular location.
表明，如果你想使用 QEMU ，跳转到的第一条指令是那个地址。
And we basically arranged for the kernel loader to load the kernel that program,
我们安排内核加载器加载 kernel 程序，
so there's a file kernel.ld that basically specifies how the kernel should be loaded,
有一个文件 kernel.ld ，指明内核应该如何加载，
and you see here that basically the first address that the kernel is going to use is actually that particular address, the [] QEMU specified.
你可以在这里看到，内核使用的第一个地址就是 QEMU 指定的那个地址。
This is how we get off the ground.
我们就是这样开始的。
Does that make sense?
能理解吗？
Okay, we see also that here, actually GDB shows the binary encoding of the instructions.
我们可以在这里看到， GDB 显示了指令的二进制编码。
And so we see that basically I guess the csrr four byte instruction and addi is two byte instruction.
我们可以看到，我猜 csrr 是四字节指令， addi 是两字节指令。
Okay, I'm going to see, basically so actually basically start at entry.S,
好的，我要看一下，实际上是从 entry.S 开始的，
with no paging with no isolation and in fact we started M mode,
没有分页，没有隔离，实际上开始于机器模式，
xv6 jumps as quickly as possible to a kernel mode or supervisor mode that called in RISC-V,
xv6 尽快跳转到内核模式或者 RISC-V 中说的管理者模式，
I'm just going to set a break point at main, which actually runs in supervisor mode,
我在 main 设置一个断点，它运行在管理者模式，
I'm gonna run there, and then I get to the first instruction of main,
我运行到这里，然后达到 main 中的第一条指令，
so, let me show this here's main,
所以，让我来显示这个，这是 main ，
I'd like to run GDB in this layout, split mode.
我想在这种布局下运行 GDB ，分离模式。
So you can see in GDB actually and what the next instruction is being executed,
所以你可以在 GDB 中看到，接下来执行哪条指令，
so you see, there's a break point at that particular instruction.
你可以看到，有一个断点在那个指令处。
Since this is run, QEMU with one CPU, just makes it GDB a little bit easier,
因为 QEMU 使用单 CPU 运行，使 GDB 更简单，
so there's now only one core active, so QEMU emulates only one single core
所以只有一个核心活跃， QEMU 只模拟了一个核心，
and I can step through that, so I can go to the next instruction
我可以单步运行，我可以运行到下一条指令，
and calls a function called consoleinit which does exactly what you imagine it does, it actually sets up the console.
调用函数 consoleinit ，它所做的就是你所想的，设置 console 。
And so once we set up the console, we can actually print to it
一旦我们设置好 console ，就能打印东西，
and so you'll see in a second we'll get a new line and we get xv6 booting.
所以，随后你会看到新的一行，看到 xv6 booting 。
Okay, so there's a whole bunch of additional code to set things up,
好的，还有一些代码用来设置，
you know there's setting up the page allocator,
有设置页面分配器，
setting up virtual memory which I'll talk about on Wednesday,
设置虚拟内存，我会在周三讨论，
loading actually starting turning paging on, which I also talked about on Wednesday,
加载启用页面，我也会在周三讨论，
setting up the initial process or setting the process table,
设置初始进程，或设置进程表，
setting up code due to the use of the kernel position,
根据内核位置设置代码，
setting up the interrupt control the plic, we'll talk about when we talk about interrupts,
设置中断控制 plic ，我们会在讨论中断的时候讨论，
but this is one thing like that, we're going to be using to basically talk to the disk, we talked to the console using interrupts,
但它是，我们使用中断访问磁盘，使用中断访问 console ，
setup the file system allocates buffer cache,
设置文件系统，分配 buffer 缓存，
initialize the inode cache, initialize the file system, initialize the disk,
初始化 inode 缓存，初始化文件系统，初始化磁盘，
and then basically once all sort of things are set up, you know when the operating system is running,
一旦设置好所有东西，当操作系统运行时，
it's going to start running the first process and this is the userinit.
可以开始运行第一个进程， userinit 进程。
So there's a little bit of interesting, so I'm going to go to userinit
这里比较有意思，所以我要转到 userinit ，
for a second and then I'm going to single step there.
稍等，我会单步运行到那里。
Before continue, any questions about this?
在继续之前，关于这些有什么问题吗？
Is there a specific order in which the set up functions need to be called?
调用这些设置函数有特定顺序吗？
Yes, some function must be run after other functions and they're in particular in there,
是的，一些函数必须在其他函数之后运行，它们比较特别，
some of them doesn't matter, but few of them it's important that they run after other ones.
其中一些无关紧要，但是有一些在其他之后运行是很重要的。
Good point.
好问题。
Okay, let me go to so userinit,
好的，让我们转到 userinit ，
and basically userinit there's a little bit of glue code, organization code
基本上 userinit 有一些胶水代码，组织代码，
to take advantage of all the general [infrastructure] [] have basically get the first process of the ground.
利用所有[基础设施]，让第一个进程启动。
You know xv6 needs some image, we can't run the file system really yet, or do exec,
xv6 需要一些镜像，我们不能真正运行文件系统或 exec ，
and so xv6 server small little program to get off the ground
所以 xv6 需要一些小的程序来启动，
and that small little program is initcode,
这个小程序就是 initcode ，
the binary version of that program is actually linked or declared statically into the kernel,
这个程序的二进制版本已经静态链接或声明在内核中，
in fact, that code corresponds to a this particular user program,
事实上，这些代码对应这个用户程序，
it's it's a little program written in assembly
它是一个由汇编代码写成的程序，
and basically it loads the address init into a0,
基本上，它加载地址 init 到 a0 ，
it loads the address argv into a1
加载地址 argv 到 a1 ，
and then it loads the number for this exec system call into a7
然后加载 exec 的系统调用编号到 a7 ，
and then look at the here that calls ecall.
然后看这里，它调用 ecall 。
So basically what it does is
它说做的是，
running three instructions and then running the fourth instructions which basically transfer back control to the, back control to the operating system,
执行三条指令，再执行第四条指令，将控制权转移回操作系统，
so generally if I set a break point in syscall, and now keep running,
如果我在 syscall 设置一个断点，并继续执行，
then basically you know userinit, you know will create the initial process and return to user space,
然后 userinit 会创建初始进程，进入用户空间，
run the three instructions or four instruction, and basically come back into kernel space.
执行这三条指令或四条指令，再返回内核空间。
So basically this is the first system call that any user application in xv6 runs,
所以，这是 xv6 中用户程序运行的第一个系统调用，
so let's see what happens at right, so, continue and we actually got to syscall.
让我们看看会发生什么，所以继续，我们到达 syscall 。
So look at syscall, we can look at it, it's a function at the bottom.
我们可以查看 syscall ，它是最下面的一个函数。
And so we're back into kernel space now, and we're going to walk through and see actually what happens exactly in syscall,
现在我们回到内核空间了，我们看看 syscall 到底发生了什么，
so I'm gonna single step a little bit, it looks about the [current] the processes within it,
我会单步运行，看看它里面的过程，
you know that pulls out the system call number, that's used,
它拿出使用的系统调用编号，
so we can now print num, and let's see that's 7.
我们现在可以打印 num ，它的值是 7 。
And if we look at, one of kernel's is syscall.h,
如果我们查看 kernel 里的 syscall.h ，
that declares all the system call numbers
里面定义了所有系统调用编号，
and we see 7 that is indeed system call exec.
我们可以看到 7 是系统调用 exec 。
And so basically this tells the kernel, some user application, called the ecall instruction
这告诉内核，某些用户程序调用 ecall 指令，
and with the intention of calling this system call for with the intention of running the exec system call.
想要调用，想要运行 exec 系统调用。
And so we can single step a little bit further,
我们可以再单步执行几步，
we go to the next thing, this is the line that executes a system call,
我们到下一步，这一行执行 syscall ，
so let's go there, and you see that basically the num is used to index into an array
让我们到那里，可以看到 num 作为一个数组的索引，
and array there's a bunch of function pointers
这个数组有很多函数指针，
and [] the SYS_exec entry, you know points to sys_exec function,
[包括] SYS_exec 入口，指向 sys_exec 函数，
so we're going to single step into this.
所以我们单步运行到这里。
And we see that we're actually at the sys_exec, so this is in sysfile.
我们看到我们在 sys_exec ，它在 sysfile 文件中。
You know we can move it a little bit more in a bigger window
我们可以在这个窗口中移动多一点，
and we basically see here, system call.
我们可以在这里看到，系统调用。
And the first thing that you see actually it actually gets arguments from user space,
首先，它从用户空间获取参数，
so it gets the path name,
它获取路径名，
so we want jump a little bit further,
我们跳的更远一些，
um memset, basically allocates space for arguments, you know copys all the arguments from user space to kernel space,
memset ，为参数分配空间，将所有参数从用户空间复制到内核空间，
we'll look down in great amount of detail in a couple weeks,
我们会在后面几周看到更多细节，
so don't worry about it too much yet.
现在不用过多考虑它。
But basically there's some code to move arguments user space to kernel space,
基本上是有一些代码将参数从用户空间移动到内核空间，
you know from the kernel from the user address space to kernel address space.
从用户地址空间到内核地址空间。
And if we now look at path, you can print the path hopefully,
我们查看 path ，你可以打印 path ，
you will see actually that you know that is a string
你会看到这是一个字符串，
and you'll see that basically what that little init code program does
你会看到那个小 init 程序所做的，
is trying to exec you know the init program which is yet another program.
试图 exec init 程序，这是另一个程序了。
So let's look at that for seconds just to see what that is.
所以，让我们看一下这里发生了什么。
So here we have init, and init basically sets up a couple things use for user space,
这里是 init ， init 基本上是为用户空间设置一些东西，
opens the console, the file descriptor for the console, dup it a couple times, calls fork,
打开 console ， console 的文件描述符，复制几次，调用 fork ，
and basically the first thing it does, actually it starts to create a new process and will exec the shell shell,
基本上第一件事情是，它创建一个进程，然后 exec shell ，
and so this will in the end, result as the shell being run.
最后 shell 可以运行。
So, for example if I would continue I probably break again, it says exec,
如果我继续，可能会再次中断，在 exec ，
and if I look at the arguments I will see that actually the exec system call is being called to execs the shell.
查看它的参数，实际上 exec 是在 exec shell 。
And once you exec the shell, you know, let's do that,
一旦 exec shell ，让我们先这样做，
then we'll do a couple more system calls and at some point you'll see that.
然后会调用更多系统调用，某个时刻你会看到。
Well, let me do continue, then basically the shell starts running.
好的，让我继续，然后 shell 就运行了。
So it gives you a little bit of sense, you know actually how xv6 gets off the ground,
所以，这给了你一些感觉， xv6 是如何开始的，
the first shell actually gets run
第一个 shell 运行，
and we saw this sort of a little bit of an overview about how the first when the first system call actually happened.
我们看到第一个系统调用是如何发生的。
We haven't really looked at the dive machinery for these system calls how to get in and out of the kernel,
我们没有深入了解系统调用是如何进入退出的，
we're going to talk about in a couple weeks or two weeks in lecture in great amount of detail,
我们会在后面几周的课程中讨论更多细节，
but this is sort of enough for you to understand actually how to do the syscall lab,
但是这对于 syscall 实验已经足够了，
you know that we assigned for this week.
这是我们这周布置的实验。
And so these are the pieces, you will be interacting with.
所以这些是你们要了解的部分。
Any questions before I wrap up, because we're almost out of time.
在我结束之前，有什么问题吗，因为我们快没有时间了。
You're free to fire away.
你可以随意提问。
Are we going to do anything with networks, so like networking and labs.
我们有关于网络的东西吗，比如网络的实验。
Yes, the last lab is you implement a network driver,
是的，最后一个实验是实现一个网络驱动，
and so you will write the code that interacts with the hardware
你需要写一些代码与硬件交互，
and you have to manipulate the registers from the network driver for the network card,
你需要操作网卡网络驱动的寄存器，
that basically connects you know to this RISC-V board,
网卡连接在 RISC-V 板上，
you know you saw that it was a block basically to plugin an Ethernet control, a cable,
你可以看到它是一根电缆，插入以太网控制器，
so there's an Ethernet card, and so you're going to be programming that card,
这里有一个以太网卡，你需要对它编程，
you're gonna actually send some packets across the Internet.
你可以真正地通过互联网发送一些包。
Great, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Yeah, it's the last lab.
是的，那是最后一个实验。
Any other questions?
还有别的问题吗？
We're gonna, let me wrap up here,
让我来结束一下，
I think the syscall lab itself, because we're not really going great amount of detail, hopefully shouldn't be too bad,
我想 syscall 实验，因为我们没有深入很多细节，希望它不会太难，
it might be easier than the util lab,
它可能比 util 实验简单，
labs, next lab, however might be more difficult,
下一个实验可能比较难，
so it's always hard to get all these labs right,
所以想让所有实验正确是比较困难的，
but this syscall lab hopefully it shouldn't be too difficult,
但是 syscall 实验不会太难，
but please don't start don't wait until the night before, get going early,
但是不要太晚开始，要早点开始，
so that if you're running some obscure bug, that we can actually help you out
如果你遇到疑难的 bug ，我们可以帮助你，
and make sure that your program works [].
确保你的程序可以正常工作。
With that, I'll sign off and I'll see you in Wednesday.
就是这些，我要退出了，周三见。